Guide to the Henry David Thoreau Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry David Thoreau collection
1841-1949
YCAL MSS 203
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.13
(2 boxes) + 2 art, 1 broadside, 1 roll
The Thoreau collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, and objects relating to Henry David Thoreau. There are several original manuscripts, including notes on insects, weather, and natural phenomena, and drafts of poems, an untitled essay, the article "The Discovery of America, and Researches in Central Africa," and the concluding paragraphs to Walden. There is also an essay on Thoreau by Francis Sheldon and George Shiras with photographs by Roland Wells Robbins and Edwin Way Teale. There are photographs of Thoreau's residences in Massachusetts, including his childhood home in Concord and the site of his cabin at Walden Pond. Objects include pieces of wood and nails from Thoreau's cabin and pencils manufactured by his father's company, J. Thoreau & Co.
Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1862
Sheldon, Francis
Shiras, George
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Henry David Thoreau Collection was acquired through various gifts and purchases dating from 1911.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
There are two cut film negatives corresponding to prints in the collection. The negatives are restricted and may only be seen with permission of the appropriate curator. Reference photographs have also been subsituted in the main files for material stored separately.
Scope and Contents
The Henry David Thoreau Collection consists of letters, manuscripts, photographs, and objects documenting the life and work of Henry David Thoreau. The collection spans the years 1841-1949.
The collection is housed in two boxes and organized into three series according to provenance: Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, Henry Seidel Canby Gift, and Material from Other Sources. Box 2 contains Oversize material.
Series I, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, consists of one letter, a brief ALS from Thoreau to the Harvard College librarian, and several holograph manuscripts. The writings include notes and drafts for poems, an article, and the concluding paragraphs to Walden. There are notes on insects for the years 1851-54 and on weather and other "general" conditions for the months of April, October, and December, with detailed charts for October and December for the years 1852-61 and 1850-61 respectively. The Aldis gift also includes the May 1852 survey Thoreau conducted for the "Noah & Joshua Brooks Farm" in Lincoln, Massachusetts.
Series II, Henry Seidel Canby Gift, consists of one holograph manuscript, photographs, and objects, and is organized into subseries for Writings and Other Material. The gift includes a heavily corrected manuscript for "General Phenomena for November" which, like the manuscripts in Series I, contains notes on weather and natural phenomena. The Other Material subseries includes photographs of a sketch of Thoreau and two sections of a stud(s), as well as two nails, from Thoreau's cabin at Walden Pond. The stud sections and nails are stored separately and reference photographs are provided in the main files.
Series III, Material from Other Sources, is organized into subseries for Writings and Other Material. Writings include a holograph manuscript for an untitled essay by Thoreau, with a typed copy, and an article on Thoreau by Francis D. Sheldon and G. Peter Shiras. The article by Sheldon and Shiras documents the history of Thoreau's "hut" on Walden Pond and includes photographs by Roland Welles Robbins and Edwin Way Teale. The Other Material subseries includes a pencil box and pencils produced by Thoreau's father's firm, J. Thoreau & Co.
Oversize material, housed in box 2, contains material from Series I and Series III.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Natural history -- Massachusetts; Concord (Mass.); Walden Pond (Middlesex County, Mass.); Artifacts (object genre); Nails (fasteners) -- United States -- 19th century; Pencils (drawing and writing equipment) -- United States -- 19th century; Photographic prints; Authors; Robbins, Roland Wells, 1908-1987; Sheldon, Francis; Shiras, George; Teale, Edwin Way, 1899-1980; Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1862; J. Thoreau & Co
- Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1841-1864; Series I; 7
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Owen Franklin Aldis, 1911
  Series I, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Harvard College Library, 1858 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - WRITINGS
    - "An[nual] Phenomena for December" notes, holograph manuscript, 1850-61
    - ["April weather..."], notes, holograph manuscript, [1860?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ["The discovery of America, and researches in central Africa"], holograph manuscript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "General Phenomena for October," notes, holograph, 1852-61
    - "Independence," poem, holograph, 1841 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [On insects], notes, holograph, 1851-54
    - "Travelling," poem, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes text on verso
    - Walden, draft of concluding paragraphs, holograph, 1864 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - "Plan of the Noah & Joshua Brooks Farm..." holograph, 1852 May (Box BSD, folder 7)
    - Tube for "Thoreau's Plan of a Farm, 1852", undated (Box 3 (Art))
- Henry Seidel Canby Gift, 1845-1846; Series II; 3
  Gift of Henry Seidel Canby, 1940
  Series II, Henry Seidel Canby Gift, is organized into two subseries: Writings and Other Material.
  - WRITINGS
    - "General Phenomena for November," notes, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - OTHER MATERIAL
    - Stud sections and nails from Thoreau's cabin at Walden pond, [ca. 1845-46] (Box ART, Folder 9)
      Includes letter, dated April 14, 1932, from Henry Seidel Canby
    - Pencil sketch of Thoreau by D. Ricketson, photographic copy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Material from Other Sources, 1850-1949; Series III; 6
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Sources indicated on individual folders.
  Series III, Material from Other Sources, is organized into two subseries: Writings and Other Material.
  - WRITINGS
    - Writings of Henry David Thoreau
      ["The great story of the night..."]
      - Holograph, [1851 Aug?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Typed version, corrected in unidentified hand (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Writings of Others
      Sheldon, Francis D. and G. Peter Shiras
      - "A House Which I Had Myself Built," essay, typescript, corrected, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Includes photographs by Roland Wells Robbins and Edwin Way Teale
  - OTHER MATERIAL
    - Pencils and pencil box from J. Thoreau & Co. (Box ART, Folder 14)
    - Printed ephemera, 1938, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Surveyor's certificate in Thoreau's hand, 1850 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Oversize, 1850-1949; 0.92; (1 box)
  - Holograph manuscript for "An[nual] Phenomena for December" (In Series I), 1850-61 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Holograph manuscript for "General Phenomena for October" (In Series I), 1852-61 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Holograph manuscript [On insects] (In Series I), 1851-54 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photographs from "A House From Which I Had Myself Built" (In Series III), 1949 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reproduction of sketch by D. C. Sturges (In Series III), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 21)